All right. Hello, welcome everyone. It's
May 15th, 2025. This is active in for
ant stream 14.1 and we're going to begin
it as we do with a GitHub
push and we're going to go from there.
Okay, this stream is called generalized
notation notation from plain text to
triple play. And before jumping into the
background, want to give a little bit of
the payload up front. Here's the simple
structure of the repo and where we're
headed. All the source code is in src.
All the documentation is in doc and all
the output from running main goes to
output. So what is the output going to
look like? Well, first, where does it
start from and where is it going? What
it starts from is looking like a
markdown file with a controlled
vocabulary describing state spaces for a
given generative model. And here's where
we take
that. First, for each of those provided
source files, GNN files, we get a bunch
of visualizations. So anyone who's
worked with PMDP or active inference
models knows that figuring out state
spaces and doing all kinds of work in
transformations with state spaces can be
challenging. So one thing this does is
it takes that generative model
distinction as specified and visualizes
it. It outputs it. It exports the model
into a variety of formats.
JSON, text, XML, graphical, all these
different kinds of
outports. There's a initial processing
report essentially summarizing what
kinds of files are being
detected. There are rendered
simulations. So, here is a
PIMDP
script that fills in, not perfectly
functionally at this point, but I think
more than enough to get the picture, a
PIMDP script parameterized
by the details of the state space of the
source file. And where this is all going
is to be able to cross render into
multiple implementation strategies. So a
stub method for going into RX
infer type checking is performed. So
that is checking the validity of the
code and making sure that the source
files are valid. And this allows us to
bring in not just security features but
also something that is often much
desired for those running active
inference models which is the
computational resource estimation. So
here we can look at the state space
sizes and the different kinds of
operations that are entailed for a given
generative model and then get different
kinds of assessments like what is the
relative computational cost going to be
or what is going to be the size for a
given number of variables of storing
that specific model on on the RAM or on
the hard drive.
uh LLMs are used at the end to in this
case summarize a set of
questions. So here are uh reports
written with LLM
summarizing the state space
model. the
logs for improved tracking and
coding. MCP is the model context
protocol and we'll get into this a
little bit more but this is a very large
file which concatenates all of the MCP
methods which we're exposing like
visualize GNN file. So this is something
that you can run locally or we can stand
up and we will stand up MCP servers so
that these kinds of services can be
provided. Ontology processing these are
summaries of the ontology terms used and
how they map onto different state
spaces. And this is really one of the
key pieces of GNN which is putting a
little bit of space between putting a
flexible interface and gap between a
given variable and its ontological
annotation.
So commonly in looking at these
generative models and cognitive modeling
type scripts, you'll see the name of a
variable like observation modality 1 or
latent state or whatever it happens to
be some English language name of a
variable. However, that can get into
some issues because what if it's
modality 3, but then one of the other
ones comes and goes or what? How do you
add modality 4? Or it's the sense uh
variable for one agent, but it's the
action output from another agent. So in
other words, you don't want to have the
variable always welded to its onlogical
assertion because there can be multiple
English terms or roles for a given state
space variable. We're going to come back
to that with cerebrum. And then also
there can be different languages for
localization and accessibility. So
there's a space between the variable
state space and the assertion. And what
that looks like inside of the GNN
file is a specific
section that makes assertions about
ontological meaning in that exact
generative model. So gone already long
long long gone are the days where
debating whether the letter B means
transition matrix. Well, no. It's just a
symbol that in a given generative model
might be asserted to mean transition
matrix. Then those rendered
scripts. So we had the program synthesis
of the PIMDP agent parameterized from
the GNN file. And then we can actually
execute those. And this
one hit an error that you'd hit running
PIMDP and so did this one. But in
previous versions, I've had it running.
So it's just in and out all presented as
open- source work in progress. and
inserting the correct value values into
the stem and stub of a PIMDP script is
totally doable and it will be coming
when the time is right. Then there are
test reports. So this is just a
test information from a test
module and overall a processing summary
which has been improved and disimproved
and all of that. Okay, so that's where
we get with the outputs. How is this all
going to be happening? Let's pull back a
second.
If anyone has any comments or questions,
please write them in the live chat. Um,
all this is open source at the GitHub
repo active inference
institute/generalized notation notation
no
spaces. I'm using the updated version of
cursor 0.50.4
for and the large language model for
most of the augmented coding vibe coding
happening here is Gemini 2.5 Pro the
preview 0506 so just from a few days ago
okay we will briefly look at the source
structure get a first pass pull back a
little bit to the history of GNN then
re-enter into the source with people's
comments and questions so here's how
source folder looks
Okay, source folder has a main script.
So when you want to replicate the entire
process, you just go to src and run
python 3 main. So there's a single entry
point that is going to look like this.
It's going to
start go through
one, which is just confirming that it
has the GNN
payload. Go into
two, which is the setup phase. That's
going to install the requirements, any
other packages that you add into
requirements.ext. It is going to go into
three, which is the test suite. There's
just a few tests right now, but you can
add more tests. four goes into the type
checker suite which has the the type
checking as well as the resource
estimation
methods. After four, it will head into
five, the export module. And so the the
folders are not numbered, but the
scripts are just to really confirm
here's the order that we're running
these different modules in. Five goes
into the export, so you can flag
different export modalities. Six into
the visualization
methods. Seven is the MCP the model
context protocol
uh section which we'll go into more
detail. Eight ontology terms ontology
analysis. Nine is the rendering. So
that's like the setup of the simulation.
That's the transformation from the
generic GNN form and parse output into a
rendered but not
executed EG, PIMDP, RX infer, NGCLERN,
etc., etc., etc. We'll build those
adapters and they'll be really
robust. Step 10 is running the
simulation. So, actually this one, let's
see if it came through.
This is looking like it actually did do
the PIMDP
simulations. So let us
see slow computer. There we go.
So not
exactly fully functional, but this is
demonstrating
that we can do program synthesis,
controlled vocabulary, program
synthesis in an implementation agnostic
fashion with static checking, render it
into a given target implementation style
like PIMDP and then run that PIMDP the
method and it looks like there still
could be some errors in the simulation
but it is breaking on through to
the other side. That's 10. Then 11 runs
the LLM section which you can customize
and it's going to go into this LLM
processing and that's where it's going
to do things like
summarize the
uh GNN file or do a set of questions
that are responded
to by the LLM
uh and give an executive summary. Then
it's going to finish the 11th one and
give you some summaries on the whole
pipeline. So again, just while we're
overviewing the source folder structure
and then heading into the uh context and
the the history of GNN main is going to
call the 11 scripts and you could just
start up another prompt. Make me a 12th
script and a folder for doing dot dot
dot. Like if somebody writes a question
or a comment in a live chat, I very may
well add another module or do some other
method. Then each of these scripts which
are run by main are going to look into
the folder of their own name. So for
example, the type checking is going to
look into GNN type checker and it's
going to
find different files like the resource
estimator methods all of that. And so
you can choose in this sort of main
first shell layer of dispatch which
tools you want to bring into play. And
then we can advance out the tech tree in
a really modular way like okay we have
type checking on models with planning
but we don't have pimdp for it and then
we'll just go to the script where it's
working and then reverse engineer what
is the state space specification we need
to do so that we can generate that
script that did work and if we can make
that connect we're going to be able to
have a ton of flexibility and a lot of
reproducibility and integrity for the
models that we
Another feature that's going to come
into play in the MCP module is that each
module has an MCP. py script. And these
are going to be methods that become
available to the MCP module. So the MCP
module when it is run is going to look
in the src folder and say okay go into
all the folders and find the MCP.
PY and then pull all the methods from
the MCP py and that will get reported on
in the MCP processing step which is
where we get these very very information
dense super
informative very
informationrich files about which
methods we're exposing in this
implementation. So then if you're
running a version and you don't have the
execute or you have a certain version of
one of these or a different
folder, as long as you have that MCP.
py, it's going to control which services
you're giving model context protocol
availability to locally or remotely. And
so there's some super fun ways to think
about that from like a
businessinstitution perspective. Like if
it's worth one cent to verify a
generative model or to render it into
PMDP or to execute it, then maybe with
microp payments those kinds of things
will become easier to do like X 402
which Holly uh shared in a meeting
yesterday. Um, and big picture on the
MCP, this is an example of a neuro
symbolic architecture because there can
be generalist agents, multimodal agents,
whether they're probabilistic models
like neural networks, transformers,
LLMs, etc., or it's a person with a pen
and paper and index card. By opening up
this GNN stack as an MCP nexus, we're in
a new space where the LLM can do program
synthesis and
execution on generative models. So it
can be using its own weights, its own
inference methods to do certain things
including tool switching. And then if
there's a given situation where explicit
planning is needed, it's not that we
need the LLM or the neural network to do
explicit
planning, but it could spin up a
simulation and dispatch the execution
that does do explicit planning. So like
if you go to an LLM and you say, "Hey,
what's the expected free energy of me
doing this on this day?" It might give
you a number or it might give you some
relative variable and and that might be
directionally accurate. It might be
valid. Might be good enough. So it's not
to say that it's not. But what it's not
doing is doing program synthesis on a
generative model and then using free
energy minimization to actually work on
that model and leaving a full type
checked trace all along the way.
So that's the sort of neuros symbolic
programming aspect that is going to be
super interesting. I always think of
this like a chocolate chip cookie where
the soft cookie part is like the
generalist probabilistic agent and then
the chocolate chips are like the GNN or
the tools that it can call through MCP
or through other techniques. So we now
have really good dough better and better
and really good chocolate fragments
better and better too. So there's a lot
of opportunities for this kind of
crystal embedded in a more liquid or
gelatin-like interface that is going to
enable models again that don't have
explicit planning or other features like
that to drop in and deploy these actual
simulations with really strong
reproducibility and tracing. Okay. So,
where did this GNN concept come from?
And meanwhile, of course, anyone can
write a comment or a question and I'll
hope to bring some new features into the
package like by the end of the
stream. So, this work was during 2022
and
2023 working with Yakobmeckl who's
currently a graduate student at
Stanford. We were doing various things
with multi-agent systems and having a
lot of fun talking about active
inference and AI and whatnot and we
started to explore this idea of making
notation systems that were
implementation agnostic for active
inference and using that for our own
epistemic and pragmatic ends. So for
example in the
stepbystep active inference paper of
Smith first and white from 2022 this is
like a common step up in terms of
learning about generative models. So
like in the top left there's D which is
a prior and latent states S the latent
state itself like the temperature in the
room O the observation on the
thermometer and then A the mapping
between the real temperature in the room
and the thermometer. So it's a static
onetime step perception. You got a prior
on temperature, a thermometer reading
coming in and then through the ambiguity
matrix A, you come to some posterior on
latent state. Then you can add one more
motif in with a B transition matrix.
Then you can have temperature changing
through time emitting observations with
thermometer readings. This is a passive
inference.
It's a partially observable marov
process. Then that can get bumped up to
a partially observable marov decision
process in this case where the
decisioning is represented by this pi
policy vector of
affordances which are operated on by an
expected free energy functional which
intakes a c preference vector. And then
that can even be extended further to
have this E habit vector and then this
precision temperature kind of shaky hand
on action stuff happening. So it's like
okay how do we really look at that
though and
understand ideally in an open- source
plain text way really get down to what
are the specific similarities and
differences between these models. And so
that led to us which we jokingly called
LAN gauge because of gauge theory. Um
where these are plain text and you can
take a given column from like the KOD
and you can just paste it into a notepad
and it will come out like a markdown and
it has different sections and it's a
pretty similar structure today two years
later. Looking in the GNN examples,
looking here, we see some of those
similar fields and a similar state space
notation as to what it was where you
declare the state space, you declare the
connections, give initial
parameterization, add any other
equations, how is time treated, what is
the annotation of the ontology. Um, and
then we could have other sections like
what's a footer or we could have a
cryptographic signature. So that was
version one of the paper in the earlier
days of active inference institute fun
where we wanted to highlight that we
could bring together all these different
ways of thinking about program synthesis
and we could express it in what is also
the title of the stream which is the
triple play. So the triple play is the
highfidelity rendering of a GNN
expression whether it's a small motif or
whether it's a whole ecosystem scale
multi-agent generative model a hybrid
synthetic intelligence etc etc
etc across and here's the triple play
plain text graphical and executable
computational forms moving in and out of
these forms and that's the triple
So then we talk a little bit about those
three aspects of it. The the textbased
model, plain text, benefits of plain
text, graphical models here of course
playing on the double play of graphical
itself being like a graphical relational
model but also being visual,
diagrammatical, graphical and then the
executable cognitive models. So
sometimes you just want to like dream a
big dream about a recipe, but there's
recipes you can specify that you can't
cook at home. You just don't have the
ingredients or no kitchen could possibly
do this or that. So separating out where
are we just writing creative speculative
semi-fiction generative model play? When
are we
visualizing the aforementioned? And then
when do we really want to execute it?
And when it gets down to executing it,
just like software can be implemented on
different operating systems, we want to
be able for flexibility and
reproducibility to execute cognitive
models in different settings. So that
was our paper. uh we summarized that
shortly and then we provided a quick
assessment on how this GNN is actually
not just useful and pragmatic, it's also
very epistemic. So we dive a little bit
into the realism and instrumentalism
topic and then we talk about how we will
be able to implement this triple play.
And here we are in that ballpark, the
very same implementing the triple play
and even planting some seeds that
bloomed many many April showers and May
flowers later. Like from a linguistics
perspective, it would be interesting to
explore possible grammatical case
systems, morphology, and dialects
associated with GNN. It's not just a
throwaway line. That's what cerebrum is
about. case systems for generative
models. So now we can say well we want
the locative version of that GNN. And so
for those who are wondering where does
cerebrum come into play? How can I use
what I've learned from Sanskrit and
Russian and Latin and is invisible in
English? How can I use that kind of
morphological morphos syntactic
understanding of language? How can I
bring that to high reproducibility
generative modeling? Here is how. And
that was the paper in 2023 with Yakob
and put it on the back burner for a
little bit. But now the repo is
back with a
uh Fury, but not an Angry One. And
hopefully this is going to be a
really key tool and platform for people
who want to use
generative models for education and for
research and it can be under the hood.
It's not that every single person may be
in this exact repo. But as we start to
think through these things as a
community, it becomes a lot clearer and
clearer how having these methods for
setting up
workspaces, testing our environment,
type checking and resource estimation,
exporting and confirmation, visualizing
generative models, making methods
available for LLMs and other
agents, understanding the onlogical
annotations of state spaces, preparing
ing simulations through rendering
executing the simulations and using LLMs
to give interpretability in natural
language and do other kinds of
operations like these are some of the
core activities that we need for our own
research work. So it's cool that we can
develop this and make this an open
science space
um and welcome participation from from
people who see opportunities and
challenges here. So let's do a few.
Let's check out the agenda and see where
we might want to do something. And then
again, if somebody's watching live, they
can write a comment or an idea in the
chat. So what is GNN and why is it
important? GNN is a plain text
notational style and tradition that
focuses on statesbased definition of
generative models. For example,
statistical models or cognitive models
of agents. Why it's important is that
with that kind of a controlled
structural vocabulary for generative
models, it's possible to reproducibly
and at high throughput engage with a
whole sequence of different kinds of
functionalities ranging from
reproducible environment setup and
testing, typeing, resource estimation,
exporting, visualization, accessibility
to MCP, ontological analysis, rendering,
execution, LMS, and beyond and more. So
that's pretty cool and important. Core
concepts are woven throughout and the
goals are for us as always on these
kinds of streams and at the institute
where everyone's welcome to find out
more and participate is to increase the
accessibility, rigor, and applicability
of active inference. And so this is a
triple play on that triple play.
How does GNN allow for clear textual
specification of complex models? So, we
can look at what it looks like now, but
with more advanced automated code
generation, for example, the autogen lib
may be one
uh library to look
into as well as
kit. So, kit is
a code synthesis library. So right now
this is like a V 0.1 or a V1 version of
the GNN spec. It isn't that it has to be
written this way with this section
title. It's just to give an idea and
then we can use more advanced code
templating methods to generate these
from possibly even a more distilled
condensed version that renders into a
GNN that then gets used. But that's kind
of like the assembly code question. Um,
so how does GNN allow for clear textual
specification of complex models? Well,
by separating out a few key steps.
Separating out first in the state space
block the sheer declaration of the size
and type of different variables.
So C is going to be length three vector
float. Or you could say, well, I'm I'm
going to be able to do my C vector with
integers. Then you could say it's an
int. And then in the resource and
checking, you could know that you could
work with integer calculations. So
that's the state space block. Then
connections, which is a little bit
generic. Of course, these need to be
nuanced a lot to be really used as a
base graph, but the information is there
after the state space block and the
structural specification is the initial
parameterization. So
here it could be done in a more pythonic
fashion or it can be just fully
specified out what is the initial state
or a given kind of renderer could have a
default like if something is not
provided with initial state it's
defaulted to uniform or to the identity
matrix. So whatever kind of rendering
rules you
want and then you separate out the
ontology annotation. So you've already
basically initialized the space of the
model and initialized the values and now
you have this annotation layer which
could easily be swapped out with a
different
language. Okay. So that's kind of a a
2023 brought into current year plain
text version of what a minimal GNN looks
like which is just a focus on some free
form contextual information about the
generative model state space for
initialization with initial
parameterization and the ontology
annotation. And we've been having some
great convos in the multi- aent meetings
about well what space does that leave
open then for the orchestration and the
message passing and the communication
all these kinds of logistics and
operations of generative models. But
that's where actually again the cerebrum
and the case system comes into play
because if the generative model let's
just say is the ingredients like that we
have um lentils, mustard and vinegar.
And then there's a sentence in the
recipe which is like the orchestration
specification like with the mustard in
the kitchen put
the sauce on the lentils and then being
able to look at all those prepositions
and understand which of the cases are
each of the models being used in. Oh,
it's with the mustard but it's on the
lentils. But then if lentil has multiple
methods or multiple different
characteristics and it turns out like
with the lentils is really hard on the
GPUs because they're heavy but putting
something on the lentils doesn't mean
that we need GPUs at all. So that's
where we get case specific resource
estimation through this kind of metal
linguistic intelligence
layer key syntax and structural elements
just went through them. Okay, Triple
Play with GNN. And
and no, I I'm not just talking about the
everpresent comprehensive who's on first
style dialogue between Professor Phineas
Cogwell and Pipsqueaky Wheeler as they
discuss the GNN format. I'm not just
talking about that triple play. I'm
talking about
the representation triple play which the
LLM invented another triple play of
understanding conversion execution but
it works well too so Levy okay
showcasing GN in action practical
examples of the triple play so let us do
that and also see a little bit about how
cursor does this kind of
lowkey high throughput high efficacy
program synthesis so let's make a new
example
and work within the framework we already
have and then we can explore some more
far out things.
So write a new
example GNN
file fully compliant
like these
two
for a pom dp where the ontology
assertions are in Spanish terms.
There are more
submatrices for each
variable, but
still compatible
with just just these are just kind of
reminder
notes. But in in a in a better world,
which we may already be in, these don't
even matter, but still compatible with
visualization
methods. And the situation is that it is
a trading algorithm
being run on an
airplane where if it loses money then
the
plane runs out of
gas. Okay. So with all this kind of
documentation and context and especially
templates and examples in the niche then
Gemini or whomever you call will be able
to make a new example. though let us see
we're seeing into that that chain of
thought that inner dialogue that Gemini
is having with itself and it's starting
to think through okay so here's what we
have to
do this kind of pseudo thought that's
happening and then it's writing out all
these details so it'll pop up a file
soon
okay meanwhile so welcome Andrew I'm
going to copy in
your
question. So now now we're in the game.
Let's just get a few uh interesting
things done during the rest of the
stream. Okay.
Andrew wrote, "Could a 12 involve
putting together some dashboard of the
visualizations and/or metric reporting
or some synthesis between LLM stage and
visualization?
Sure. Let's do let's make one new
folder called site.
This this I'm sure could be done
automatedly too, but I'm just going to
manually make an MCV. py
uh mainly bring in the
init.
Um
then okay, stop
thinking. Continue. Most used command,
right? Okay, started up a new chat agent
in cursor over here. And so I'm going to
drag
in main readme and site and
say write a
file in
src. Again, just dragging it in for
explicit reference.
for 12 site.
py which will call on all the methods in
site folder make them
all
comprehensively for making a
website single HTML file with
different
sections which reflects
the output
folder, eg embedding all the
visualizations and LLM outputs and
etc. Okay, we're still deep in the
thought chain. Okay, we're we're in the
air we're in the Spanish-sp speakaking
airplane trading palm DP
example. So, it's kind of funny uh and I
guess apt, but for those who have looked
at the
2022 active inference
textbook, this is kind of like the
chapter 6 approach. And it's also the
same thing that for years we've been
working on in terms of just like what is
the recipe for cognitive modeling like
wow it sounds really cool about doing
all this active inference work but how
do we really go from there being a
situation of interest and then whether
for whimsy and fun or just delight or
something more professional like systems
engineering or doing something like an
analyst would. How do you really go from
just a system of interest to having a
cognitive model in hand? And chapter 6
from the 2022 textbook took that part of
the way and it gave like a sort of proto
recipe, but this is bringing it into
another level of structural
possibilities. And not to constrain
either, more like a playground where
there's all kinds of fun jumps and
pull-ups and swings you can do because
your expressivity is higher with these
kinds of structures and tools if you
know what's
up. So, airplane trading on the palm DP.
So as per requested we have the Spanish
language ontological assertions but the
whole point is it doesn't change
anything with what the uh state space
block or any of the initial
parameterization is. So let's accept
that. I'm going to clear the
terminal, delete the output folder just
to be sure and then rerun Python 3 main.
So in an ideal setting which we do not
know yet if we are in or not we will
have a seamless
welllogged step through of the new GNN
trading airplane trading palm DP it
should just work. So we'll we'll see if
we get there but bigger picture we know
that we can get there. We're going to
see will it make the visualizations that
we want.
So, here
comes this
is
okay. Here's the airplane
trading. Yeah. So, now we have the the
uh we have the variables from the
airplane with their Spanish onlogical
assertions being rendered. So it's like
single prompt. You don't need to know
about the details. You can go in there
and you can do the engineering and set
the specific state spaces. Oh no, no,
no, no. We wanted it to be six, not
three or whatever it happens to be. But
again, big picture, we can render
simulations for all of these generative
models to our heart's delight. So will
this script run? Well, I mean, again, we
can sort of find out. Did it run? What
happens? Yeah, not sure if the run
script worked perfectly, but again, it's
just a question of okay, what model
class is rendered what way and then
expanding that out. So that's one key
feature to demonstrate which is just
purely within cursor let alone using
more more sophisticated methods. We can
do oneshot program synthesis or really
like meta notation
synthesis and use that to just play into
the same
well-typed
pathways so that we can make a Spanish
localized
uh simulation about doing trading on an
airplane right off the bat. So that
might take a while if you were going to
manually write all those state spaces.
So, I'll just drop that one into
archive.
Okay.
So,
okay. So, that was a example of making
an making a new generative model.
So we are again like update your priors
if you're not here and seeing this. We
have single shot chat mediated capacity
to write certain structures of
generative model and then there's a lot
of work to be done so that increasingly
general
styles of GNN can be parsed and rendered
and so on. But that's actually why the
the whole suite is structured as it is
because I suspect that if we confirm
which version of GNN we're working in,
set up our workspace, run the tests, do
the static checking, export and confirm
that the export was successful,
visualize it, and then execute and uh
large language model it, we're going to
be in a great spot.
Okay. So, Tatia Zot, I'm going to read
your
comment. You wrote, "My best friend.
Thank you. Can you prepare group Discord
page your YouTube channel? I want to
join you." Yes. Please go to
discord.activeference.institute
um and you'll you'll find the discord
link. So for those who are in the live
chat now, I'm just I just went to
welcome.activeinference.institute.
That's like the landing page if you want
to get involved. We do have a discord
and you're totally welcome to to join in
and I'll paste the link just directly
into the YouTube live chat as well. Um
and that's one place activity happens,
but it happens wherever you are. There
you are.
So here we go with the uh demonstrating
a sort of package level flexibility in
terms of being able to bring in a new
functionality into the GNN space. So
here we have the
site
folder coming
together and then it will make a
12 site. py and then it will add that
into main so that it runs 12 site so
that when we add a new example
in and we run it all with
main that will have it all pop up. So
let's do another
example. So here I've created src site
MCP. So this is
like a way to confirm yeah these are the
methods related to the website like
generate pipeline summary site that's
going to be exposed through MCP. It's
not fully functional yet, but it's all
there. So that uh people could
call sequential MCP calls and then say
like here's the recipe. You blend up A,
then you add B, take two of C and
combine them with D, then do all this
and do that and then that. So that level
of uh programmatic
synthesis is something that is very
excitingly on offer from
DSPI which is a programming structure.
It'll look a little cleaner in the
repo for
doing program synthesis at the level of
LLMs, which is where we're going to have
the MCP
at. So, DSPI is going to be useful for
programming sequences of MCP type calls.
kit or something similar is going to
allow program synthesis and codebase
level
intelligence. MCP whether it's fast MCP
or another method is going to support
making these tools available even if
somebody doesn't have the whole repo
because we can offer an
endpoint. Um as earlier mentioned
cerebrum and this sort of lexical
intelligence paradigm is going to help
us make case specific renderings of
generative model. So that when we
understand from the beginning what
different
roles a given object or generative model
is going to serve, we're going to be
able to understand what kinds of
rendering pipeline are needed. So again,
like if we're talking about a table, are
we talking about placing something on
the table or are we talking about
hitting a nail with the table? Because
if we're just going to place something
on the table, we only need enough RAM to
pick up the object that we're putting on
the table. Like we're going to put the
pen on the table. But if we're going to
put the table on the pen, then we need
something like a GPU that can pick up a
table. So that's how prepositions are
and what they signal. And then there's
just again these these folders can can
have more documents and more different
frameworks brought in. X42 which we were
talking about yesterday is just thinking
okay how could we do microp payments so
that if somebody thinks I'm going to
ring up the institute and ask for a
textbook written in this language and
then we do that on the back end or I'm
going to have a generative model written
up like this then there can be small
charges or just kind of authentication
different kinds of methods to to offer
these up as as services.
Okay, the pipeline 12 is integrated. So
let's see if the main can
handle this
running. So just clear I'm going to
delete
the output folder. That's why the output
folder is standalone
because how satisfying to have SRC and
doc. That's it. And this is like the
minimal dual channel strategy.
Basically, doc is suggestive that it's
going to be more natural language like
src is suggestive that it's going to
host all of the code and it is that
way. And then we have a few top level
scripts. So we have the citation if uh
anyone sees relevance in the work
partially filled. I'll change the
release date to
today for version
0.1.0. Code of
conduct auto written but we can tweak
that too.
contributions already. Even those just
listening or watching or reviewing
summaries
thereof, it's people and agents like you
that make GNN such a great tool. It's so
true. License MIT license for now. Those
with more insight into how we can have
more advanced and multi- channelannel
licenses get in touch, etc. But that's
where it's at for now. And as far as I
understand, it's the first program
synthesisbased generative model creation
assistance tooling framework. So I hope
that people who find value in that can
get in touch, maybe support the
institute, maybe support the project,
maybe use the framework. The readme is a
overview
summary. We have a cyber physical and
cognitive security policy in this GNN
project. So inquire within for more and
we do want to try to be supportive. So
whether it's during this live chat and
you have questions you want to ask or
whether you have GitHub issues that you
want to open up or other questions about
like what can we do with this, how can I
etc. then we're there for support. But
these are kind of the top level files
and all of the operational stuff is in
source. all of the extraneous
documentation as well as uh different
other ideas like how could this be
useful for multi-agent simulations like
well maybe we expand the GNN structure
to include an agent block and then we
have a GNN file that is the notation for
a multi-agent simulation and it says
you're going to use one instance of you
know five instances of this GN GNN and
one instance of that
GNN and so we can make structured
notational fields for doing all that
kind of simulation level reproducibility
and communication so that and then we
can uh
have either kind of uh state spaces that
are wired up again separate from their
English name. So we can flip in and out
of using that state space representation
where the variables could be known like
by their cryptographic hash
uh all the way on through just okay now
you want to turn it into this language
lens. So just ideas about how we could
use GNN and structured fields for the
the communication questions and keeping
with this spirit and inspiration that
it's implementation agnostic. GNN isn't
the rendered version that's executable.
GNN is the notation
notation generalization.
So if a given kind of simulation level
or agent level description is written in
GNN like DNA like source code then you
may have a rendering element that is
able to render and transform the
contents
into the format you
want. That's docs. Okay. Pipeline has
finished. It says uh successful 11 one
success with a warning. So let's see
what the
site. Okay, looks like 12 thinks that
the site was created. So let's find out.
Okay, here's the summary site. Moment of
truth.
wouldn't say it's the uh most advanced
site that I've ever
seen, but it does the
job. It has all the
information and then that's how you
develop modules. just like okay now
develop site to be like
this so here I'll just remind it of
that ensure the readme includes site and
the 12th script make any
improvements within the site
folder ensuring you
use separate scripts within site if it
is getting like long modular
methods.
Okay.
Clear. So it will take some
uh some work some collaboration from
hopefully all to many of
us that will make it more rigorous. For
example, having a strict
template of a certain kind like hey, if
you want to do discretet time, discrete
state spaces and get it to land the
plane in PIMDP, here is the standard
example or here's the code template, the
code generation template, the kind of
stuff we can do with uh code generation
libraries. Here's the code generation
library format
schema for if you want to make sure that
it's going to go into PIMDP. Well, like
this should be like this and you need
this, you can't have that,
etc.
Um, let's add a little functionality
with RX
infer. So while the website stuff is
happening, assess and use at web search
to understand how RX infer at model
statements
are
used. Eg
the generative
model joint
distributions in format
where it can be parsed by RX
infer into
a executable model.
Then make those improvements
to so
that here's the
rendering. So
that rendered outputs
are accurately conveying all the
information make and RX infer dot or
utils
py
or rx infer
utils.jl if needed.
Yeah, the Gemini 2.5 sometimes stalls
out kind of randomly. Uh we'll we'll
just say, "All right, I'm going to make
this edit." And then just hangs there.
Uh
but generally speaking, it has been
great.
Okay,
let's
add another example. See if we can get
into some other kind of model that we
uh Okay, so we have website chugging
away
here. RX infer improvement
here. Now we're going to write another
example.
According to these compliant
examples,
write another kind of generative
model, not a POM
DP that will creatively and
functionally demonstrate
important
Features and capacities
of
[Music]
package. Make the situation something
esoteric yet
tangible. Semicolon. available though
ineffable. Make it best best best
possible.
Okay.
Um, it's been 1 hour.
If some super awesome funny stuff
happens, I might stay on. But otherwise,
just a few more minutes because I think
I have pretty much conveyed where it's
at and some of the core features. So, in
the last section here, like if anyone
has an idea for an example or another
function that they want to see or they
have a specific question that they would
like addressed in this stream, please
write it in the next few minutes.
Okay.
Okay. Greetings, Andreas. Oh, now that
could be a fun a fun plot twist to
include some of your work into this.
Okay, I'll make a just a sort of starter
pack
NTQR and a uh
NTQR or
GNN NTQR.
R
MD just leave that there for now, but
I'm I'm sure that you and
others could uh imagine a few different
ways that that NCQR comes into play.
Uh it could be like a
module offered in a multi-
aent simulation setting like just as
another module you could run on top or
after the multi- aent then you can run
it with this NTQR
layer. Just trying to delete this but
it's a slow computer.
Okay. Okay. So, this is what the uh the
esoteric
Oh, goodbye cursor. It was good to know
you. Pull
quit. Okay, we're back.
Okay. All right. So, it's a GNN basian
network that stochastically generates a
verse concept. It aims to model the flow
of poetic inspiration from emotional and
elemental inputs to concrete poetic
characteristics. So, pretty cool. This
is getting us into the uh space of of
explicit active inference language
models. So not just using the inputs and
outputs of language models and treating
those or conditioning those with active
inference but this is actually getting
into what we can now do. Now make
another
example absolutely
comprehensive and
vast called an active inference language
model that has state spaces for eg
sound
ponym
syntax morpho syntax semantics
situational
narrative, all the nested and
interacting levels so we can really
truly actually finally
seriously
safely and beneficially have a full
GNN
based model of language.
No
training data sets here. Just
oneshotting the triple
play based upon the GNN
launchpad for making the
world's first
actual
active
inference
linguistic
intelligence
agent toolbox.
box. Okay. Have it continue with RX
infer cuz I got quit
on and looks like the website one did
too. We'll just say continue and then
we'll we'll run it again in a few
seconds.
Yeah, also the new version of cursor
050. It has some background. Well, one
important thing indexing was broken out
into its own separate tab. If you've
watched a bunch of in for ant streams,
you know that I was always going to like
features and then scrolling down to the
codebase and and doing the reync. Um,
there's
MCP, but this is exactly how easy it's
going to be to then have all this GNN
stuff tucked away and then point the MCP
server at it. So then other people or
agents will be using cursor or whatever
and then it'll be like plan make a plan
and then that could invoke this program
synthesis rendering type checking
visualization simulation execution
multiple environments logging etc etc
etc website generation
um and also there's the
uh background agents
I don't know
where it is in the settings. I haven't
looked at it, but there's a background
agent that you can
have. So that could be very useful. For
example, a background agent could say
always absolutely vigilantly be
assessing if everything is totally good
and up to mega standards for everything
we're doing. And just let us know if
not, but don't make changes by yourself.
Okay. AI
LM
phonetic target and
articulation. Let's see what this looks
like. So again, if this were using
motifs and the structure that we knew
was going to
work, then
like we would know it would work.
Okay, let's close that
chat. See if the website is done. All
right, here we go. We're going to throw
caution to the wind and see if this
active inference language model will run
in PIMDP. It's It's not going to. Well,
let let's delete the output just to
confirm. Delete the output
folder. Okay, so let's just see how it
broke it up. see how the LLM broke up
this structured analysis. And this is
just a total total early hint of the
power of using language models and
general purpose agents to write
structured texts which we
then can bring into this explicit
program execution framework. Okay, so
hidden state factors, phonetic target
and articulation.
Then there's a lexical morphos syntactic
level. So lexical concept ID that would
be like the diction like table chair.
Then there's the current syntactic rule.
This takes us right back to cerebrum and
the different grammatical cases like is
the table
acting? Is the table the recipient of
action? Is something being placed on the
table? Is something being placed near of
the table? And then there's tense,
number, gender, etc.
That brings us from the sort of lexical
into the more properly fragments of
semantics which here let's see semantic
proposition. So a propositional
availenced
propositional assertionbased semantic
representation not the only one but
that's why we can make multiple kinds of
GNN files. We could say make a new GNN
file that explores a really really
different and radically contrasting
semantic
concept narrative context internal goals
and
predictions observation
modalities you can make no no we only
want it to observe auditory we want to
have confirmation that the observations
are only coming in through sound and
that all the semantics is being
endogenously
generated or we we want the policy
output to be red, yellow, green, just
three states or we want the policy
output to be words in the dictionary
then we would have literally next token
prediction policy prediction in this
kind of
ailm would be just like it is in
transformers. So this state space block
is obviously
massive.
Um the
connections. Let's see if the
visualization went
through. Okay, here's the poetic muse
model.
Interesting. Here's the poetry
model. Ontology assertions in the state
space.
That one was
oneshotted. And then let's look at the
language
model. Okay, looks like it has some
differences that um so that we could get
to this state space representation, but
that the but
like it it could be a breaking change.
But the kind of uh suggestion would be
drag this in. Hey, we didn't get all the
visualizations that we thought of.
Ensure that visualizations are generated
properly for
this and then it would be off to the
races
again. Exports. Here's its attempt to
export it in JSON style. So maybe you
only need to use maybe you're when
you're calling MCP or you're you're
using this for your own research, maybe
all you want to do is specify it, type
check it, and then export it. You don't
even want to visualize it. Or maybe you
you just you don't care if it's type
checked, you just want to visualize it.
So that's why these methods are are
written out separately.
Uh this is
the language model failing to be put
into PIMDP format. Let's see if it gets
a little bit
better. And similarly RX infer
uh didn't continue
through comprehensively ensure that at
model blocks really are output
to
there given the GNN input.
So maybe I'll run one
more.
Okay. Okay. Refactor the
website. All right. So we we'll let this
uh RX infer update come
through. But we could in the LLM when I
just interrupted
it. That would be
So here we get that LLM
um
interpretation
generated from an OpenAI call at this
point to describe the
model and to to answer different
questions about the model. So you can
have a default question kit q kit ask
these different questions.
Um let's see what happened when it was
trying to execute
it. Yep. A matrix must be a numpy array.
At least it's a real
error.
Okay.
Um,
so where to go is going to depend on
where you're at, what time it is, all
that kind of
stuff. I hope that
people look through, contribute,
improve.
I think one of the most high yield
payoffs if somebody is
uh familiar with structured code
generation methods or type checking um
or program synthesis techniques would be
to develop a
uh
template. not not to fix it as like the
one and only template to use, but just
here's a template that we can reference
all of the other methods
against and and uh also know which
degrees of freedom we're going to be
able to to
uh move with and
break because right now it maybe we'll
say oh well um you know the
visualization wanted there to be a a
hyphen here and then you add the hyphen
here and the visualization works but
then the other you know something else
doesn't work. So that is where I believe
that using this order of
operations is going to be helpful or
something similar to it of course
pending everyone's input but basically
like
first verify that the GNN module is
loaded up and use this file structure
and
punctuation to confirm you're like yeah
this is the version of GNN we're working
with this is what the symbols mean
then but that that should just output
the documentation and the version. It
shouldn't need any requirements to be
installed in the workspace.
Then setup also it's kind of standalone
and simple but it it should install the
requirements that are needed. then an
extremely comprehensive test suite can
be run including tests about later
modules. So maybe there's more maybe
there's a module that's not used in your
flow but still it is type uh checked and
tested with a
template. The type checking is basically
the first of the real ingress steps and
this is where I know that there are
better methods that that people can
bring to the
table. Okay, let's let's run main one
more time just to see if it can get this
RX infer plane landed.
Okay, so GNM type checker uh maybe the
resource estimator could be broken out
to its own
uh
script or or folder even. But the
resource estimation is not costly. So I
figured it probably can stay with the
type checking because it is based upon
the inferences made by the static type
checker
engine export that that could go
slightly earlier
uh because you don't need to type check
but type checking tells you yeah this is
you're going to have an issue with with
this variable it's not stated properly
or like you won't and then export kind
of confirms that that you can read in
and out. So if everything is green light
up on through export, the goal is like
you should be in the clear because we've
already done static testing. We've
already demonstrated that we can read in
and then read out a given file. So like
downstream of five, I think it it may
even use the re-exported
form after having already been checked
to be the same as the input. So it's
like if we can regenerate the original
GNN file 100%.
then we may want to work with that
airgapped version purely because on one
hand it's like it'd be the same but on
the other hand it's a version that we
know that we
wrote
visualization there there could be
generic and specific visualization
methods and so that would require a lot
of flagging like where are we doing heat
maps where are we doing other kinds of
visualizations
MCP again that that could be moved to to
a different uh order but it should
expose these methods and the
neurosymbolic possibilities for MCP use
like imagine the so-called language
models the transformer
LLM
calling the real language
model as program
synthesis and then that
active inference probabilistic language
model could have a GNN dialect. So it
could do program synthesis on
GNN within a linguistic GNN
representation inside of a cookie of
just probabilistic general
inference ontology. That one could just
be more of an archival uh latter note.
It doesn't have to be eight, but it's
pretty interesting. Like if we wanted to
say, hey, this undergraduate course or
this microcertification or training, you
are going to fully understand this drone
forest simulation example. It's a multi-
aent simulation with drones in a forest.
Here's the file that we are going to be
looking at and everything is going to be
about those ontology terms. So, every
single thing we say is going to be
semantically laser eye on your education
related to drones in the forest. And we
can have one foot in that content and
still pivot out and associate and talk
about other topics, but let's be clear
with which ontology terms we're using in
a controlled fashion.
render maybe another word is slightly
preferable but this is just preparing
the simulation for
execution. So having a render like a
prepare and then the execution phase may
just be as simple provably as Python and
then the Python script name. That would
be ideal. Doesn't do any other stuff. It
just pulls the trigger on what render
loaded
up. LLM again here you can just say make
it so that LLM does this other kind of
thing. That's just more general LLM
tools and then today on the stream we
made this site to generate it. So let's
uh in the closing bit. Okay, let us look
at the RX
infer to see if if we got a
better RX infer
simulation. Okay, that one
didn't. That one didn't. Okay, so
program synthesis for RX infer waits
till another day. One thing that's going
to be awesome with RX infur specifically
is another degree of freedom where we
will be able to specify RX infer models
and then we could either run that
locally or dispatch that to the RX and
FUR server
API. So then that's like earlier I said
you can write recipes that you can't
cook but this is like separating out now
it's like you can write a recipe that
you know you can order because you can
fully specify it and then send it to the
to another endpoint that's just an RX
and first server that will run your app
model with your
conditions but you've already done the
type checking and the verification. you
know that you're working off of a
generic implementation agnostic
representation. Okay. And the LLM is
still um processing. So let us
uh let that finish then pull in the
site. But in terms of the last um
content here, we will
uh read a little bit from
the plain text to triple
play. So, we're going to improve this
with one prompt and then see if anybody
uh has any comments or questions after
reading it. We'll write a new who's on
first dialogue.
Triple
play. Write a new novel
dialogue. Who's on first
style? Whimsical and deadly
serious. Total Americana. Deep lore.
Absolutely conveying all the topics with
quote triple play
puns related
to dragging the dock folder in such that
through the reading of
such the SRC code becomes
strangely obvious to those who pay
attention. Again, this must be
like
absurd
speculative
realism for a variety of reasons.
delivered in PhD dissertation
length who's on first dialogue
style or it could
be three
conversants if that will make the
triple play pun play all the
Thank you, Andrew
[Music]
P. Okay.
We could have like a we could do a
benchmark on how much do each of these
LLMs know about 1920s baseball
more.
Okay, while that chain of thought
proceeds, let's just see the LLM
stuff. So, it's written four of the
five. So each each um
currently in the GNN folder examples is
the target input
directory. We might want to have another
directory called input or something so
that it's just obvious which files are
going to be
uh iterated through. But obviously
that's one of the
um ways to work
faster. If you only have one uh file in
here, like it's going to happen way
faster. But right now, it has to do all
the iterating and looping
for all five of these examples. So I
think I'll move
I'll move three of them into
archive just so that people can get
started and get it running
faster. But the language they all could
be developed in
versions in really fun ways.
Okay.
Okay. We'll generate this dialogue and
then if there's any uh last
comments to see what else is in the docs
folder about GNN. This just summarizes
that's a starting place. Here's a domain
specific language DSL spec sheet for
it. A uh more human legible
uh examples breaking down the different
examples. file
structure these kinds of markdown
representations
uh mermaid plots super
useful. How does it get
implemented? Again the goal and the
whole vision is
like specifying generative models at a
level above implementation. So if if
you're on a Intel versus an AMD
processor, the program is still going to
work. So similarly, like if you're going
to be exe, there might be some features
that are easier or only available within
one of
these computer languages or within one
of these implementation environments.
But in principle, we're talking about
specifying something at at a more
semantic level.
uh as mentioned and alluded to a little
bit, I think that this kind of
executable program synthesis is going to
have a lot of relevance for
neurosymbolic synthetic hybrid
intelligence
architectures. There's a whole world of
multi-agent
specification and ways that we can work
at this layer.
Okay,
Gemini, one more
chance really fully write out
this
conversation which we need.
Uh here's the plain text or a summary of
it of the paper itself, but it's linked
in the in the repo with
Yakob. Some information on the syntax,
but this could be reflected probably
better using this type of
kit
concept.
Uh,
no. This is the repo. Paste
/kit. Codebased mapping, symbol
extraction, code search, building LLM
powered, developer tools, agents, and
workflow. When I saw that, I was like,
yes. and making MCP servers access to
it.
Uh that's basically the the docs just to
review what's there.
Now X42 microservices RX infer we can
make a
PIMDP folder just to
be leaving a stub there.
And that could have like more generic
documentation information on doing GNN
PIMDP, but it it'll just
be to
be. All
right. Here we
go. All right. I'm going to push it on
GitHub. read this uh oneshotted
dialogue. Oh, the LLM is
still working for some
reason. Okay.
uh read the dialogue and then either it
will uh either it will end on an
extremely dramatic funny note we haven't
looked at it yet or maybe somebody will
have an appropriate comment or question
in the next minute or two at which point
I will then read that
one. So here we are in other triple play
dialogue. Okay, here we
go. The GNN triple play
A dialogue in three fits and many errors
characters Abner double day earnest
precise a true believer in the system
capitalized. He's trying to explain the
rules of generalized notation notation
GNN. He often clutches a heavily
annotated copy of what looks like a rule
book but is in fact doc/GNN file
structure doc.
Casey Specs Stumble, an old-time
baseball manager, weathered, full of
Cracker Barrel philosophy and prone to
spectacular
misunderstandings. He's always looking
for the angle or the specs on the new
talent and how this all plays out on the
diamond, which he sometimes confuses
with the GNN connections graph. He
squints at everything through thick
smudged spectacles. branch. Ricky
Wright, a shadowy, almost spectral
figure. Perhaps a long disenfranchised
league commissioner, a rogue
statistician, oh brother. Or a
philosopher of the great American
pastime, now haunting the onlogical back
alleys of model
specification. He speaks in aracular,
often unsettling pronouncements, his
voice like the creek of an old stadium
gate. setting the deepest, dustiest back
office of the National Generative Model
League,
NGML headquarters. A forgotten annex
that smells of old leather, stale
cigars, lenammen, and the faint sharp
tang of ozone from ancient calculating
machines that were rumored to predict
not just game outcomes, but the very
fabric of fan belief.
Yellowed schematics of factoraphs and
basets are pinned to the peeling
wallpaper, interspersed with faded
dgeray types of stern-faced men in
bowler hats who might have been
pioneering
statisticians, spiritualists, or perhaps
both. A single fly specked gas lamp
sputters erratically, casting long
dancing shadows that make the GNN
diagrams on the wall seem to shift and
writhe. A ticker tape machine in the
corner occasionally coughs out cryptic
decontextualized messages. Eg. model
name not found, state space undefined,
policy does not
converge. The curtain rises, or rather
the dust mo swirl expectantly. Abner is
pacing, occasionally tapping his
rulebook. Specs is trying to whittle a
piece of what might be a broken bat or a
very large pencil with a pen knife.
Rickety is half hidden in the shadows,
only a glint of an eye and the
occasional wisp of pipe smoke visible.
Bit the first. Who's our model
name? Abner clearing his throat,
adjusting his spectacles. Gentlemen,
welcome. Or rather, welcome back to the
eternal deliberation. Today we must
rigorously define the parameters of our
our understanding. It all begins as it
must with the model name. Clarity here
is paramount. Specs. Model name. Eh, is
he a new kid? What's he about? Lefty,
righty? Got any pop? We need pop. The
fans, they scream for pop. And where's
he from? Don't tell me he's another one
of them fancy college boys who can't hit
a curveball in the state space block.
Abner size. A small puff of dust rises
from his wa waist coat. No specs. model
name isn't a player. It's it's the
designation, the unique identifier for
the entire conceptual architecture we
are attempting to instantiate. Think of
it as the banner under which the whole
enterprise marches, the grand title on
the spine of the
almanac. Select the team name, the
generative giants, the notation
nationals, the markoff chain marauders.
I had a team once, the Mudville 9. Good
bunch of fellas. Terrible fielders. Lost
17 straight in the time horizon. 17.
Each discreet time step of fresh
agony. Rickety voice rasps from the
shadows like dry leaves skittering
across an abandoned home plate. The
name. Yes. Before the word there is the
naming. Before the connections are
drawn, the model name is whispered into
the void. It is the first casting of the
die. the initial prior block from which
all subsequent beliefs unfold. Does the
name sing to the act infotology
annotation or does it merely echo in the
empty grandstands of failed
hypothesis? Precisely, Mr. Wright. Well,
almost. It's less about singing and more
about unambiguous
referencing as stipulated in doc/file
structure doc. MD section 2. It's a
descriptor, a label. For example, GNN
PMDP agent. Concise,
informative. PMDP agent sounds foreign.
Is he one of them international league
fellas? Got a good arm. This agent, can
he play multiple positions? Like, can he
cover hidden state and also fill in
observation if we're in a
pinch? Versatility. That's the ticket in
this league. A real triple play threat
if you catch my
drift. Abner massaging his temples. It's
PMDP refers to the Python library for
marov decision processes. The agent is
the model itself. It's not about
positions on a field specs but about
variables in a
system. Variables. Eh. So like guys who
are inconsistent, hot one day, cold the
next. We got a whole roster full of
variables.
S_F0 couldn't hit water if he fell out
of a boat last Tuesday. And Ocore M1,
don't get me started on Ocore M1's
fielding errors. Cost us the penant that
one. Initial parameterization was all
wrong for
him. Rickety, the initial
parameterization, the primordial soup,
the conditions at the dawn of the
simulation. Was the bag cked from the
start? Were the dice loaded in the state
space block? Or was it merely a
d_f0 set to uniform ignorance awaiting
the harsh lessons of
observation? Yes, the d_f0 vector the
prior belief over initial states for the
factor zero. You see specs model name
sets the stage. Then comes the model
annotation.
Model annotation. Is that the fellow who
writes down what model name does? Like a
scorekeeper or one of them newspaper
scribblers always looking for a model
name to tear down. We had a guy Scoop
Mcury used to say my policy vector was
more like a meandering suggestion. The
nerve Abner the model annotation is a
free text caption specs. It explains the
model's purpose, its context. It's
ras. It's the color commentary if you
will to the model names playbyplay. It's
where you describe the triple play of
GNN, the textbased specification, the
graphical model intuition, and the
executable cognitive model. Triple play.
Now you're talking, Abner. So model name
is the batter. Model annotation is the
guy on first.
And who's on second? Is it State Space
Block? He sounds like a big fella, a
slugger. This is going to be a long time
horizon. State Space Block isn't a who.
It's a what. It's the where. It's the
definition of all possible states the
system can be in. The dimensions of a
diamond
itself. I'm going to skip on since
there's many
sections to the end, but let's skip.
Okay, last
section.
Abner looks from specs to rickety a
dawning realization or perhaps just
fatigue in his eyes. So, src/main.py
py that orchestrates the one GNN
parsing, the two setup environment
configuration, the three export
transformations, the four GNN type
checker validation, and the five render
execution. That's just the Empire
calling the game, ensuring the rules of
generalized notation notation are
followed. The Empire, of course, that's
main.
always sticking his nose in, checking
the GNN version and flags, and making
sure the footer and the signature are in
order. Thinks he's God or G or some
other fancy letter, but without him,
it's all just
output/log/kaos.txt. Rickety, the main
py, the silent orchestrator, the loom
upon which the GNN tapestry is woven. It
does not judge the model annotation's
poetry nor the equation's elegance. It
merely ensures the pipeline flows from
text to graph to
code. A humble servant of the triple
play. The true mystery, gentlemen, is
not who's on first or what's on second
or even I don't know on third. It's why
we play the game at all. And for that
answer, you'll need to consult a model
name far grander than any found in
SRC/GNN/amples. Rickety fades further
into the shadows. Spec starts idly
checking model parameters on an
imaginary bat. Abner stares at his GNN
rule book. A single bead of sweat
tracing a path through the dust on his
forehead. The ticker tape machine
clatters one last time. Simulation
complete. Observed outcome unlikely
under current priors suggest revising
world
models. Or perhaps the rules of the game
itself. The gas lamp sputters and dies,
plunging the room into near darkness,
illuminated only by the faint residual
glow of unvalidated hypothesis.
All right, thanks everyone. Hope this
was pragmatic and epistemic for you.
Looking forward to people's feedback and
collaborations. Acting first surf.